<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Descritpion of Devon Record Office, Deposit 2507 (Ex)</title>
                <author>Timothy L. Stinson</author>
            </titleStmt>

            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Siege of Jerusalem Electronic Archive</edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Society for Early English and Norse Electronic Texts</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>

                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>United Kingdom</country>
                        <settlement>Exeter</settlement>
                        <institution></institution>
                        <repository>Devon Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>Deposit 2507</idno>
                        <msName>Ex</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>

                    <head>
                        <title></title>
                        <origPlace>England</origPlace>
                        <origDate notBefore="1450" notAfter="1500">On the basis of the handwriting, the manuscript seems to date to the second half of the fifteenth century.</origDate>
                    </head>

                    <msContents>
                            
                        <msItem>
                            <p>A fragment of <title>The Siege of Jerusalem</title> <ref target="http://www.cddc.vt.edu/host/imev/record.php?recID=1583">IMEV 1583</ref> corresponding to Hanna-Lawton 985-1017 and 1106-1138.</p>
                        </msItem>

       

                    </msContents>

                    <physDesc>

                        <objectDesc form="codex">

                            <supportDesc material="paper">

                                <support></support>


                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="leavesCount" n="1">A portion of one folio</measure>
                                    <measure type="pageDimensions" n="28 x 6 cm">A paper strip about 280 x 60 mm. Hanna-Lawton estimate that the original leaf would have measured approximately 325 x 275 mm.</measure>
                                </extent>

                                <foliation>None</foliation>


                                <collation> 
                                    
                                    All that survives of this copy of <title>The Siege of Jerusalem</title> is this single strip of paper, which was discovered during restoration work on the memorandum book of <persName>Furse of Morshead</persName>, in which it had been incorporated as a binding strip. The discovery was publicized by <persName>Michael Swanton</persName> in <date when="1990">1990</date>. The fragment contains only portions of thirty-four lines of text on the front and thirty-three on the obverse. The surviving lines correspond to Hanna-Lawton 985-1017 and 1106-1138; this gap of eighty-nine lines may not be the exact number missing in Ex, but must at least be quite close to the actual count (the fact that the text is presented in two columns makes this count higher than one would ordinarily expect from two sides of the same leaf). Because it is impossible to ascertain what the original line numbers would have been, the lines have been numbered beginning with line 1 and continuing consecutively even though this gap exists; as with other manuscripts, however, the lines are also keyed to Hanna-Lawton's line numbers, which reflect both the gap between the lines on the front and back of the leaf and the location of the text approximately 1000 lines into the poem. The front and back of the fragment, meanwhile, have been designated <locus from="1r">1r</locus> and <locus from="1v">1v</locus>.
                                </collation>

                                <condition>Fragmentary</condition>

                            </supportDesc>


                            <layoutDesc>

                                <layout columns="2">
                                    <persName>Swanton</persName> notes that "[t]he writing-space is apparently complete at the lower edge, with a <measure type="written">2.5 cm</measure> bottom margin; the upper edge has been cropped however, with perhaps seven lines of writing cut away" (103). What survives of the manuscript suggests a careful presentation of the text in a codex with high production standards. <persName>Swanton</persName> suggests that it is "more grandly set out than any of the extant copies hitherto known" (103), although it was certainly rivaled, and perhaps exceeded, by U. The poem was originally copied in double columns, a practice unusual for poems written in the alliterative long line and occurring elsewhere in the surviving corpus of <title>Siege of Jerusalem</title> manuscripts only in P. 
                                </layout>

                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>


                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>
                                <p>The text is written in a clear anglicana script. There is no evidence of medial punctuation, but the cropping is so severe that no full half-lines survive, and thus it is not possible to see whether the caesura was marked. Although linguistic evidence is scant in a fragment of this size, Hanna-Lawton are able to offer some helpful observations about the dialect: "The fragment is far too brief for any definitive linguistic analysis, although it generally appears to be in a central north Midland dialect (Notts.? Derbys.?). The copyist has <hi rend="italic">-es</hi> in the present third person singular but <hi rend="italic">-en</hi> in the plural, <hi rend="italic">o</hi> for OE <hi rend="italic">ā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">shall</hi>, <hi rend="italic">them</hi>. One unusual form, 1006 <hi rend="italic">thurw</hi> "through" (although at the edge of the fragment and conceivably the remains of <hi rend="italic">thurwe</hi> or <hi rend="italic">thurwh</hi> or <hi rend="italic">thurwȝ</hi>) is recorded in LALME (3, 591-92, grid 472 456) as the majority form of but a single scribe, LP 228, from the upper <placeName>Derwent</placeName> valley just northeast of <placeName>York City</placeName> (perhaps <placeName>Kirkham</placeName> OSA?)."</p> 
                                
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>





                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote>
                                <p>One rubricated paraph survives at what would have been Hanna-Lawton line 985.</p>
                            </decoNote>
                        </decoDesc>


                        <bindingDesc>
                            

                            <p>Not applicable</p>
                               

                            
                        </bindingDesc>

                    </physDesc>


                    <history>
                        <provenance> Nothing is known of the origins of the manuscript other than it was found in the memorandum book of <persName>Furse of Morshead</persName>, "a family from <placeName>Kingsbridge</placeName>, south <placeName>Devon</placeName>" (Hanna-Lawton xix).
                        </provenance>
                    </history>

                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source>
                                    <bibl> </bibl>
                                </source>
                            </recordHist>
                        </adminInfo>

                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl><editor>Hanna, Ralph</editor> and <editor>David Lawton</editor>,
                                eds. <title>The Siege of Jerusalem</title>. EETS o.s. 320.
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>,
                                <date when="2003">2003</date>.</bibl>

                            <bibl><author></author>
                                <author>Swanton, Michael</author>. "A Further Manuscript of <title>The Siege of Jerusalem</title>." <title>Scriptorium</title> 44 (<date when="1990">1990</date>), 103-4.
                            </bibl>
                            
                            
                        </listBibl>


                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <!--
<revisionDesc> <change who="" when=""></change> </revisionDesc>
-->
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
